Amos E. Dolbear Papers MS016
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- The Telephone Appeals and patent related documents, 1877 -- 1894; MS016.003; 2.45 Linear Feet; 12 Volumes
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Brief for complainants on motion for preliminary injuction, 1882; MS016.003.011.00004 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Closing argument of Causten Browne for the defendants, 1882; MS016.003.011.00005 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Defendants' answer, 1883; MS016.003.011.00006 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Defendants' points: Arguments of J. E. Maynadier, esq., 1883; MS016.003.011.00007 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Evidence for defendants', 1883; MS016.003.011.00008 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Hearing on motion for preliminary injuction: Closing arguments of Chauncey Smith for plaintiffs, 1882; MS016.003.011.00009 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: On motion for interlocutory injuction: Evidence for defendants, 1882; MS016.003.011.00010 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Opinion of the court, 1883; MS016.003.011.00011 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al.: Before Gray and Lowell, J.J.: Opinion of the court, 1883; MS016.003.011.00012 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, MS016.003.011.00013 (Box 11)
  - Deposition of Amos E. Dolbear (part), MS016.003.011.00014 (Box 11)
  - Description of the Dolbear telephone system, MS016.003.011.00015 (Box 11)
  - Did Reis invent a speaking telephone? Opinions of scientific men, 1886; MS016.003.011.00016 (Box 11)
  - Dolbear's new telephone system, 1881; MS016.003.011.00017 (Box 11)
  - Evidence for the defendants: American Bell Telephone Co., et al. v. Albert Spencer, et al., MS016.003.011.00018 (Box 11)
  - Hearing before the Department of the Interior (Bell), MS016.003.011.00019 (Box 11)
  - Hearing before the Department of Interior (Bell), MS016.003.011.00020 (Box 11)
  - High Court of Justice, Chancery Division: The London and Globe Telephone and Maintenance Company, Limited v. The United States Telephone Company, Limited: Judgement, 1882; MS016.003.011.00021 (Box 11)
  - Patents filed with the Commissioners of Patents for Inventions, London, 1881 -- 1882; MS016.003.011.00022 (Box 11)
  - Philipp Reis der erfinder des telephon (in German), 1878; MS016.003.011.00023 (Box 11)
  - Records of experiments made by H. C. Buck under the direction of A. E. Dolbear, 1879 -- 1881; MS016.003.011.00024 (Box 11)
  - Sound vibrations and the telephone, 1879; MS016.003.011.00025 (Box 11)
  - Supreme Court of the United States: Amos E. Dolbear et al. vs. The American Bell Telephone Company: argument of Wheeler H. Peckham, 1886; MS016.003.011.00026 (Box 11)
  - Supreme Court of the United States: Dolbear et al., appellants vs. The American Bell Telephone Co.: argument of Causten Browne, esq. for appellants, 1886; MS016.003.011.00027 (Box 11)
  - Supreme Court of the United States: Amos E. Dolbear, Francis M. Holmes, and Henry B. Metcalf, appellants vs. The American Bell Telephone Company: brief for appellants, 1886; MS016.003.011.00028 (Box 11)
  - Telephone clippings scrapbook, 1881 -- 1894; MS016.003.011.00029 (Box 11)
  - United States Patent Office: In the matter of the interference between Amos E. Dolbear, George L. Anders, and Thomas A. Edison: brief for Dolbear, 1881; MS016.003.011.00030 (Box 11)
  - United States Circuit Court for the Eastern District of Louisiana in Equity: American Bell Telephone Company v. National Improved Telephone Company: On motion for preliminary injunction, 1885; MS016.003.011.00031 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States, District of Massachusetts in Equity: Westinghouse Electric Company v. Sun Electric Company: Opinion of the Court, 1888; MS016.003.011.00032 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States, District of Massachusetts in Equity: Westinghouse Electric Company v. Sun Electric Company: Brief for complainant, 1888; MS016.003.011.00033 (Box 11)
  - United States Patent Office: Speaking telephone interferences: Interlocutory proceedings under preliminary interferences, 1878; MS016.003.011.00034 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States, Southern District of Ohio, Eastern Division: The government telephone suit: Hearing on motion and plea of the American Bell Telephone Company against jurisdiction in Ohio: Argument of Grosvenor Lowrey for the United States, 1886; MS016.003.011.00035 (Box 11)
  - In the United States Patent Office, before the Examiner of Interferences: William W. Jacques v. Henry F. Campbell: Interference, electrical conductor: Brief of argument in behalf of Campbell, 1883; MS016.003.011.00036 (Box 11)
  - United States Circuit Court, District of Massachusetts: Westinghouse Electric Company vs. Sun Electric Company and M. M. M. Slattery: Brief for defendants in reply, 1884; MS016.003.011.00037 (Box 11)
  - United States Circuit Court, District of Massachusetts: American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear, et al., before Gray and Lowell, JJ: Opinion of the Court, 1883; MS016.003.011.00038 (Box 11)
  - United States Circuit Court, Eastern District of Louisiana: the American Bell Telephone Company, et al. versus the National Improved Telephone Company, et als.: On motion for injunction, pendente lite: Argument of J. R. Beckwith, counsel for National Improved Telephone company, MS016.003.011.00039 (Box 11)
  - United States Patent Office: Before the Commissioner of Patents in person: James W. McDonough vs. Alexander Graham Bell, Elisha Gray and Thomas A. Edison: Interference G on telephone receivers: Brief for McDonough, 1885; MS016.003.011.00040 (Box 11)
  - N.Y. Superior Court: the Atlantic and Pacific Telegraph Company against George B. Prescott and others: Argument of E. N. Dickerson, Esq., 1877; MS016.003.011.00041 (Box 11)
  - Circuit Court of the United States, District of Massachusetts in Equity: Westinghouse Electric Co. vs. Sun Electric Company, et al.: Brief for Sun Electric Company and M. M. Slattery, by J. E. Maynadier, 1888; MS016.003.011.00042 (Box 11)
  - United States Circuit Court for the Eastern District of Louisiana in Equity: American Bell Telephone Co., et als. versus National Improved Telephone Co., et als.: On motion for preliminary injunction, MS016.003.011.00043 (Box 11)
  - Before the Secretary of the Interior in the matter of the petitions concerning the Bell Telephone patents: Suggestions in support of petitions by Mr. Clayton, 1885; MS016.003.011.00044 (Box 11)
  - "Admissions" in Bell vs. Dolbear, 1885; MS016.003.011.00045 (Box 11)
  - Advertising flyer: Dolbeare's Portable Writing Arm, 1878; MS016.003.011.00050 (Box 11)
  - United States of America vs American Bell Telephone Co., et. al.: Complainants exhibit "Index rerum" referred to by Prof. Dolbear in his deposition, 1891-11-23; MS016.003.012.00001 (Box 12)
  - Affidavits, MS016.003.013.00001 (Box 13)
  - Affidavits, MS016.003.013.00002 (Box 13)
  - Affidavits and correspondence, MS016.003.013.00003 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, MS016.003.013.00004 (Box 13)
  - Telephone, MS016.003.013.00005 (Box 13)
  - Telephone history, miscellaneous correspondence, affidavits, agreements, etc., MS016.003.013.00006 (Box 13)
  - Transcript of record. Supreme Court of the United States. October term 1886. No 113. Amos E. Dolbear, Francis M. Holmes, and Henry B. Metcalf, appellants, vs. the American Bell Telephone Company. Appeal from the Circuit Court of the United States for the District of Massachusetts. Filed October 8, 1883, 1883 -- 1886; MS016.003.018.00001 (Box Volume 18)
    Dolbear, Amos Emerson; Metcalf, Henry B.; Holmes, Frances M.
  - Telephone suits. Circuit Court of the United States. District of Massachusetts. In equity. Bell telephone company et al. v. Peter A. Dowd part I pleadings and evidence. Chauncey Smith, J.J. Storrow and C.E. Hubbard, for complainants. Causten Browne, George Gifford and Wm. D. Baldwin, for defendant, 1880; MS016.003.019.00001 (Box Volume 19)
  - Telephone suits. Circuit Court of the United States. District of Massachusetts. In equity. Bell telephone company et al. v. Peter A. Dowd part II exhibits of complainants and defendant. Chauncey Smith, J.J. Storrow and C.E. Hubbard, for complainants. Causten Browne, George Gifford and Wm. D. Baldwin, for defendant, 1880; MS016.003.020.00001 (Box Volume 20)
  - Supreme Court of the United States. October term 1886. The telephone appeals. 113 Amos E. Dolbear et al., appellants, v. the American Bell telephone company. [general] brief for American Bell Telephone Co., appellees., 1887; MS016.003.021.00001 (Box Volume 21)
  - Supreme Court of the United States. October term 1886. The telephone appeals. 113 Amos E. Dolbear et al., appellants, v. the American Bell telephone company. oral argument of Mr. Storrow on the Bell patents - the Reis defence - infringement, January 24 to February 8, 1887., MS016.003.022.00001 (Box Volume 22)
  - United States Circuit Court District of Massachusetts. in equity. American Bell Telephone Company v. Amos E. Dolbear et al. pleadings and proofs for final hearing, 1883; MS016.003.023.00001 (Box Volume 23)
  - Circuit Court of the United States District of Massachusetts. in equity. No. 2377 Westinghouse Electric Company, complainants, v. Sun Electric Company et al., defendants. volume I. pleadings and evidence, 1887; MS016.003.024.00001 (Box Volume 24)
  - Circuit Court of the United States District of Massachusetts. in equity. No. 2377 Westinghouse Electric Company, complainants, v. Sun Electric Company et al., defendants. volume II. exhibits, 1887; MS016.003.025.00001 (Box 25)
  - United States Circuit Court, District of Massachusetts. in equity. Westinghouse Electric Company vs. Sun Electric Company and M. M. M. Slattery, brief for the defendants, 1888; MS016.003.026.00001 (Box 26)
  - In the High Court of Justice, Chancery Division, Lincoln's Inn, Monday, 8th May, 1882, before Mr. Justice Fry. the United Telephone Company, Limited, v. Harrison Cox- Walker & Co. ninth day, MS016.003.027.00001 (Box 27)
  - In the High Court of Justice, Chancery Division, Lincoln's Inn, Monday, 1st May, 1882, before Mr. Justice Fry. the United Telephone Company, Limited, v. Harrison Cox- Walker & Co. fifth day, MS016.003.028.00001 (Box 28)
  - In the High Court of Justice, Chancery Division, Lincoln's Inn, Monday, 24th April, 1882, before Mr. Justice Fry. the United Telephone Company, Limited, v. Harrison Cox- Walker & Co. first day, MS016.003.029.00001 (Box 29)
  - Articles of incorporation: The American Cable Company of New York, 1880; MS016.003.030.00004 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
  - The Telegraphic Journal and Electrical Review, 1882; MS016.003.030.00005 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
    Pencil annotation on cover table of contents points to a Letter to the Editors, pp. 179-80 titled "The Telephone" and signed "Justice."
  - In the High Court of Session, First Division, Edinburgh: the United Telephone Company (Limited) v. Alexander Maclean, Edinburgh. Specially reported for the Telegraphic Journal and Electrical Review, 1878; MS016.003.030.00007 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
- Photographs and plaque, 1949; MS016.004; 1.2 Linear Feet; 1 Artifact(s)
  This series contains photographic materials and one plaque. With a few exceptions, all are portrait photographs of Amos E. Dolbear. Other subjects include a photograph of Dolbear's house on Professors Row, a photograph of Eugene B. Bowen, '76 with Benjamin L. Dolbear, Dolbear's son, and the tablet honoring Dolbear given by Bowen, Richard E. Dolbear, Dolbear's grandson, holding an electric gyrostat, another picture of the gyrostat, and two unidentified photos.
  - Amos E. Dolbear commemorative plaque (Ballou Hall), 1949; MS016.004.001.00003 (Box Shared 10)
    Heavy metal plaque. Amos Emerson Dolber, Professor of Physics, 1874-1906. Inspiring teacher -- creative scientist. Within these walls Professor Dolbear invented in 1876 the first permanent magnet telephone and the electrostatic telephone in 1879 for the transmission of speech without wires. Presented by Eugene Bucklin Bowen of class of 1876, in memory of his teacher. 1949.
  - Photographs of Amos E. Dolbear, MS016.004.011.00048 (Box 11)
    This folder contains portrait photographs of Amos E. Dolbear. No Date available
  - Photographs related to Amos E. Dolbear, MS016.004.011.0049 (Box 11)
    This folder contains a photograph of Amos E. Dolbear's house at 134 Professors Row, samples of the equipment he invented, his grandson, Richard E. Dolbear holding an electric gyroscope, and Eugene B. Bowen, '75, pointing to the plaque honoring Professor Dolbear, which he gave to the College c. 1949. No Date available
- Correspondence, 1874 -- 1969; MS016.005; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains Dolbear's professional correspondence, condolence letters and family materials, and correspondence and materials written and collected by colleagues representing him at the London and Paris exhibitions of 1881.
  - Professional correspondence, 1874 -- 1909; MS016.005.001.00001 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
  - Condolence letters and family materials, 1910 -- 1969; MS016.005.001.00002 (Box MS016 Shared 1)
  - Colleagues' correspondence and materials relating to exhibitions in London and Paris, 1881; MS016.005.001.00003 (Box MS016 Shared 1)